I'm happy to share that I have a new
book coming out in March 2026. It's
titled The Terrible Paradox of
Self-awareness, and it explores many of
the same themes found in this video and
on the channel. It's available for
pre-order now, which you can find
through the link in the description. It
was likely in a sliding glass door, a
window, or a mirror, something you had
been around many times prior. Only this
time was different. It changed
everything. For the first time, likely
at some point between the ages of 1 and
two, you recognized your reflection. You
saw you, a face, clothes, a body,
something that belonged to you, that was
you.
As you aged into and through childhood,
your reflection began to lose its
potency. It became a commonality of
everyday existence. Your concerns with
it likely turned mostly superficial. how
your hair or makeup looked, if there
were any pimples or blemishes on your
face, how your clothes draped over you
or showcased your tastes. That strange
experience of the newness of
self-awareness waned into the backdrop
of your reflection, though it remains
somewhere in frame.
Perhaps occasionally, while glancing at
a mirror in a bathroom or a car, we
might pause and experience an intimation
of it. The glance turns into a stare and
we wonder, "What is that? Am I really
inside there?" made of and contained by
this body, a brain lodged somewhere in
there asking these questions. How did I
end up here? Why and how am I a human?
In the words of anthropologist and
writer Ernest Becker, we see in plain
sight that we are in a heartp pumping,
breathasping body, a material fleshy
casing that is alien.
If we look even closer, perhaps putting
our nose almost right up against the
reflecting surface, we might suddenly
come to the visceral realization that
our skin is wrapped around us. We might
find our attention on the pores, the
small hairs, the flakes or red marks. We
might realize how much of us is
happening independent of us. The hair is
always slowly growing out, the flakes of
skin always peeling and falling away,
the oil always forming and rearranging.
Our eyeballs move around in our skull,
observing our reflection as it appears
back in their small black pupils, which
seem to consume reality like black holes
sucking everything up into the
singularity of consciousness.
Regardless of how frequent or explicit
one might experience this kind of
moment, arguably all of us do experience
a similar kind of phenomenon on a
regular basis, just with less conscious
intensity and explicitness. Every time
we interact with or perceive others,
there is at least a faint recognition
and awareness that others can or are
perceiving us. Depending on who we are,
this recognition and awareness might be
far more than faint. Regardless, in all
cases, a feedback loop of mutual
perception and objectification ensues.
We perceive and judge each other from
the outside, mapping assumptions onto
behaviors and behaviors back onto
assumptions. Other people become like
mirrors. We see our reflection in their
gaze and we feel the existential weight
of being alive and aware. Describing the
way our sense of self emerges through
social reflection, sociologist Charles
Kulie coined the term the looking glass
self, which he defined as a three-fold
process. First, we imagine how we appear
to others. Second, we imagine how others
judge our appearance. And third, we
experience some sort of pride or shame
associated with these imagined judgments
and form our self-concept partly based
on these feelings over time. Kulie
writes, "As we see our face, figure, and
dress in the glass and are interested in
them because they are ours, so in
imagination, we perceive in another's
mind some thought of our appearance,
manner, aims, deeds, character, friends,
and so on, and are variously affected by
it."
This also echoes a core concept in the
work of 20th century existentialist
philosopher Jean Paul Sartra who argued
that our sense of self is significantly
shaped by imagining the perspectives
that others have of us. Our
self-consciousness is revealed, exposed
and often distorted through the gaze of
others, perhaps creating more of an
existential prism than a mirror. And in
our attempt to interpret and align with
how others see us, we often modify
ourselves, including our own
self-perception. This was famously
explored and expressed in Sartra's play,
No Exit, where three characters who have
just died find themselves confined
inside a small room with no windows or
mirrors. At first, they don't fully
understand where they are or what's
happening. Soon, however, with each
person now limited to knowing their
appearance and character, only through
how the others describe and judge them,
it becomes clear they are in hell being
tortured by each other. Estelle, one of
the three characters, laments at one
point. But how can I rely upon your
taste? Is it the same as my taste? Oh,
how sickening it all is enough to drive
one crazy. The torture is their
self-nowledge being constrained and
affected by the others whose validation
and control always seems to elude them.
This is where Sartra's famous line comes
from. Hell is other people.
Arguably, this is why it can often feel
so strange or exhausting to be seen by
others. to interact with others. We feel
a dependency on their perceptions to
understand and form our own. But in this
dependency, we are compelled to be
hypervigilant over how we come off. And
if we want to ensure we come off in a
way that is favorable, authentic, or
both, we must constantly know, oversee,
or modify ourselves. It is as if we are
both the artist and security guard in an
art gallery that solely contains the
sculpture of our being. Everyone that
walks by wants it to look a certain way
from where they stand. If we fail in our
role or feel as though we have, it's not
because we aren't good at our job. It's
because it's an impossible job to always
do well. In the words of psychoanalyst
Jacqu Lon, I see only from one point,
but in my existence, I am looked at from
all sides.
Whether it's how we change the way we
walk or talk when we encounter
strangers. Whether it's how we dress or
present our hair and makeup differently
around certain people, or whether it's
how and why we make decisions in life
based on the expectations of those
around us. We all experience the often
hellish nature of being perceived. But
in truth, hell isn't other people. It's
us. It's how much we depend on other
people seeing us certain ways. It's how
much we depend on our reflection coming
back to us as beautiful, pristine,
controllable, and as expected. Arguably,
the root of this dependency and
subsequent disqu
is the same one that causes the strange,
disorienting experience of staring at
ourselves closely in a mirror or
becoming hyper aware of our body. We
suddenly expand the scope of our
awareness beyond the surface of our
normal unmediated state, burrowing into
our being. But ultimately we don't
really know or understand what we find
in the sense of what we think we are
looking for. A solid, clear, consistent,
authentic self. We find nothing.
Everything dissolves away and only the
strange arbitrariness of our existence
remains. Often in these moments, we are
reminded that our body is something
other in constant motion largely beneath
our awareness. We are reminded that for
the most part, we played no role in
forming it or the material that
comprises it. We have merely appeared
here in this place, in this body, in
this mind, in this self. All of which,
like the body, are also in constant
motion and largely beneath our awareness
and control. In our eyes, we see the
windows to a vehicle we are
fundamentally passengers to. When we
loathe or resist this condition, fear or
fret. When we yearn for control and to
know ourselves in the world in a
unified, static, consistent form, when
we depend on things and people to always
align with our expectations and desires,
we stay in hell. Not because we don't
find an ideal stable self or world, but
because we expect and depend on what can
never be had. If instead of fretting
over or fighting it, we see and know the
flux and absurdity and contingency of
all things and we accept and embrace it,
then we see that the doors of hell are
always open. They are inside our mind
and we control and guard them. We can at
least on occasion walk out and see
beyond the confines of the small room of
judgment and fear and ego and
hypervigilance. Outside the doors,
there's nothing to resolve, nothing to
fight, nothing to understand. There's
only something to marvel at and wonder
about like a 2-year-old child
recognizing the reflection for the first
time.
And if you ever find yourself worried,
hell is always there.
If this video resonated with you, my new
book explores many of the same ideas.
The pains and wonders of being aware,
the instability of the self, and the
possibility of finding meaning and poise
despite it all. It's called The Terrible
Paradox of Self-awareness, and it's a
project I've been working on for a
while. Of course, with the book, these
ideas have much more room to fully open
up and provide you with more space to
reflect better than any video format
allows. If you've enjoyed Pursuit of
Wonder videos or any of my previous
books, I think this one might resonate
with you the most out of anything. It
comes out March 10th, 2026, and is
available for pre-order now, which you
can find using the link in the
description. Pre-orders genuinely make a
huge difference for the long-term
success of the book. So, if you're
interested, it would mean a great deal.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general, and see
you next video.